Guide to the Alexander Mordecai Bickel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1916-1975; Accession 1995-M-136
  - ORAL HISTORIES AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1930-1975; Series IV
    Bickel undertook a succession of oral history interviews near the end of his life. The first interview was conducted by Edna G. Rostow in 1973, under the auspices of the William E. Wiener Oral History Library of the American Jewish Committee. Only the uncorrected transcript is contained here. The subjects covered include Bickel's childhood, his days at the Harvard Law School, his early interest in studying history, his Jewish identity, his early attempts at finding, getting, and then rejecting a job at a law firm in New York, and his feelings about such figures as Felix Frankfurter, Paul A. Freund and Erwin N. Griswold of the Harvard Law School, and Abe Fortas and Harry Shulman of the Yale Law School. The beginning of this oral history is a transcription and then appears to become a summary.
    The second oral history interview was conducted by Yale University's Stanley Flink, apparently in early 1974. Only the uncorrected transcript is contained here. The subjects covered include the Watergate scandal, Felix Frankfurter, interaction between members of the Supreme Court and the political branches of government, and Bickel's service under John J. McCloy and Robert R. Bowie in the State Department.
    Maggie Scarf conducted the last and most extensive interview, which began in October 1974 and ended on 4 November 1974, just three days before Bickel's death. The interview ranges widely over the major and minor events of Bickel's life, from his earliest memories and family history, to his impending death. There is also a file of correspondence relating to the controversial disposition of these tapes, transcripts, and the articles or books that were to come from them. Both of the major journals for which Bickel wrote, the generally politically conservative Commentary, and the generally liberal The New Republic, wanted to publish these materials, but neither appear to have done so. These files document the struggle between those journals and their editors to claim Bickel's memory for their own. Joanne Bickel also did an interview with Maggie Scarf in the days after her husband's death. Bickel discusses her husband's final days, his funeral, and its aftermath.
    - Oral histories
      - Transcripts
        - Rostow interview, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        - Flink interviews, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
        - Scarf interviews, 1974
          - Bickel, Alexander M. [transcripts for tapes one to six and tape eight; includes correspondence] (Box 13, Folder 3-10)
          - Bickel, Joanne (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Tapes
        - Scarf interviews, Alexander M. Bickel, 1974
          - unspecified, Tape one; 1 (Box 17)
          - unspecified, Tape two; 1 (Box 18)
          - unspecified, Tape three; 1 (Box 19)
          - unspecified, Tape four; 1 (Box 20)
          - unspecified, Tape five; 1 (Box 21)
          - unspecified, Tape six; 1 (Box 22)
          - unspecified, Tape [seven?]; 1 (Box 23)
          - unspecified, Tape eight; 1 (Box 24)
        - Scarf interviews, Joanne Bickel, 1974; 1 (Box 25)
    - Photographs
      - Bickel, Alexander M.
        - General, [ca. 1948]-1973 (Box 15, Folder 12)
        - Romania [elementary school photographs], [ca. 1932] (Box 15, Folder 13)
          See also: box 18, folder 16; box 16, folder 2
        - Columbus High School, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 14)
        - Harvard Law School [Harvard Law Review, Boards of Editors] (Box 15, Folder 14)
          See: box 16, folder 3
        - Military service, 1945, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
        - Professional colleagues [including Felix Frankfurter; Calvert Magruder; Floyd Abrams; some inscribed], [ca. 1950- 1953], 1971- 1973 (Box 15, Folder 16)
          See also: box 16, folder 4
        - Yale Law School [including studies for memorial portrait], [ca. 1970], 1975 (Box 15, Folder 17)
          See also: box 16, folder 5
      - Bickel, Shlomo and Yetta, [ca. 1955], 1959 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - OVERSIZE
    - Personal Papers
      - Memorabilia
        - Awards and certificates, 1940, 1949, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Oral Histories and Photographs
      - Photographs
        - Bickel, Alexander M.
          - Romania, [ca. 1932-1934] (Box 16, Folder 2)
          - Harvard Law School, 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 3)
          - Professional colleagues, 1953, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 4)
          - Yale Law School, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 5)